<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The recantation made at Paules Crosse, by William Tedder seminarie priest the first of December, anno. 1588. VVherunto is adioyned: The recantation or abiuration of Anthonie Tyrell, (sometime prieste of the English Colledge in Rome,) pronounced by himselfe at Paules Crosse the next Sunday following, in the same yeere. Seene and allowed according to the order appointed.</title>
            <title>Coppie of a recantation made at Paules Crosse</title>
            <author>Tedder, William.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1588</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 37 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 15 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A73302</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 23859.7</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S124616</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99899014</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99899014</idno>
            <idno type="VID">150763</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A73302)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 150763)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1979:3)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The recantation made at Paules Crosse, by William Tedder seminarie priest the first of December, anno. 1588. VVherunto is adioyned: The recantation or abiuration of Anthonie Tyrell, (sometime prieste of the English Colledge in Rome,) pronounced by himselfe at Paules Crosse the next Sunday following, in the same yeere. Seene and allowed according to the order appointed.</title>
                  <title>Coppie of a recantation made at Paules Crosse</title>
                  <author>Tedder, William.</author>
                  <author>Tyrrell, Anthony, 1552-1610? aut</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>23, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed by Iohn Charlewoode, and VVylliam Brome,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>At London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>anno. Dom. 1588.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>A reissue of "A coppie of a recantation made at Paules Crosse", STC 23858.5, with title page reset.</note>
                  <note>Title page is A2.</note>
                  <note>Caption title on p. 7: The recantation of VVilliam Tedder seminarie prieste, pronounced by himselfe at Paules Crosse, the first of December. anno. 1588.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the All Souls College Library, Oxford, England.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Catholic Church --  Controversial literature --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Anglican converts --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-12</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-01</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-01</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:150763:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:150763:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE Recantation made at Paules Croſſe, by William Tedder Seminarie Prieſt, the firſt of December, Anno. 1588.
<q>
                  <bibl>PSALME. 118.</bibl>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Impulſus euerſus ſum vt caderem, et Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus ſuſcepit me.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>I was ſore ſhaken that I was like to fall, but the Lord hath vpholden mee.</p>
               </q> VVherunto is adioyned: The recantation or abiura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Anthonie Tyrell, (ſometime Prieſte of the Engliſh Colledge in Rome,) pronounced by himſelfe at Paules Croſſe the next Sunday following, in the ſame yeere.</p>
            <p>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng" type="license">
                  <body>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Seene and allowed according to the order appointed.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>AT LONDON,</hi> Printed by Iohn Charlewoode, and VVylliam Brome. Anno. <hi>Dom. 1588.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:150763:3"/>
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:150763:3"/>
            <head>
               <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> To the Chriſtian Reader.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">B</seg>Efore you come to the reading of this my recantation, I thought good to aduertiſe you, firſt of the cauſe that mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned mee to publiſhe it in print, which is the ſatisfaction of all my Countreymen. Firſt, of them that were preſent at the pronouncing of the ſame, for though they did heare mee ſpeake in that place where I did vtter it, yet hearde they not all that heere is ſette down, for the ſhortnes of time cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed me to omitt that which I did. Secondly, I haue added ſomething more then was in that copie: ſuch are moſte of the authorities noted in the margent, out of the Scriptures, and certaine verſes, which heere I haue put downe. Third<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie, I thought it not ſufficient to haue pronounced it in one place: I know it had beene ſufficient for the aſſembly there preſent: But, my deſire is, that all her Maieſties Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iects wherſoeuer, though they heard me not, ſhold haue if it pleaſe them, a copie of my Recantation in theyr hands. Firſt to peruſe for their ſatisfaction. Secondly to prayſe God for myne effectuall conuerſion.</p>
            <p>I am nowe to entreate the Chriſtian Reader, not to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider ſo much the ſtile wherein I haue written it, as the af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection wherewith I did write it: and when you haue ſeene the ſame, I beſeech you to pray God to continue me in that good worke, which his maieſtie hath begun very gratiouſly in mee.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your harty welwiller William Tedder.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="recantation">
            <pb facs="tcp:150763:4"/>
            <pb n="7" facs="tcp:150763:4"/>
            <head>¶ The Recantation of William Tedder Seminarie Prieſte, pronounced by him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe at Paules Croſſe, the firſt of Decem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber. Anno. 1588.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Lthough euen from my childe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hoode in a manner, I haue béene noſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led vp in the faith or rather error of the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> (bothe my Parents béeing vehemently addicted to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame) Yet my fault was ſo much the greater, becauſe I did not onely obſtinatlie, but alſo in a manner deſperatly perſiſt in that Sinagogue againſt mine owne conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence. For I was alwaies diſtracted in minde with doubts of the greateſt points of that Religion. As of the Pope his authoritie. The doctrine of tranſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantiation. The preſumption of fréewill. The fancy of purgatorie. The derogatorie ſacrifice of the Maſſe, and ſuch like. In the which opinions I waded ſo far, that if the helpe of the Lord GOD had not beene at hand, it had béene to mine vtter ruine and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap>aſion.</p>
            <p>But ſéeing it hath pleaſed God to call mee backe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine, I will ſay as <hi>Dauid</hi> ſaid:<note place="margin">Pſal. 94.</note> 
               <hi>If the Lord had not helped me, it had not failed but my ſoule had beene put to ſilence.</hi> Againe, I was in greater faulte, for though I thought they could prooue theſe Articles by authoritie of Counſelles and Fathers, and as they beare men in hand by good reaſons, yet could I finde not ſo much as the grounde of one worde for them in the holy Scriptures. And thus béeing ouerwhelmed with ſo great waters,<note place="margin">Pſal. 69.</note> I was conſtrained to ſay with the Prophet: <hi>I ſticke faſt in the deepe myre where no grounde is, I am come into deepe waters ſo that
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:150763:5"/> the floods runne ouer mee.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thrée cauſes there were which kept me ſo long in mine obſtinacie and errors, which béeing compared with the cauſe of my returning againe, are of no force at all, becauſe they were fooliſh and of men: the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, was onelie of God, whoſe thoughts are not as the thoughts of men.</p>
            <p>The firſt of theſe cauſes which turned me ſo farre from the waie, was the great delight that I had in the ſtudie of Naturall Philoſophie. And in this point I was perſwaded, that I ſhoulde more profit in the partes beyond the Seas, then here at home in mine owne natiue Countrey, and therefore, partlie by the inſtigation of my Father, and partlie for the deſyre that I had to ſée forraine Countries, and moſt of all for the loue that I bare vnto y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſtudie of Philoſophie, I repaired vnto the Countries beyond the Seas, lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle conſidering the daungers that might enſue there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, as the diſpleaſure of God, the diſpleaſure of my gracious Prince, and the offence of all my Countrey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men.</p>
            <p>The ſecond cauſe, was the feare of worldly ſhame and te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>porall diſcredite, for I feared that then, which I finde nowe to bee true: which is, that they which were once my fréendes, would become my mortall e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies, which by experience I know. I did not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider then, or els I cared not for that ſentence of our Sauiour:<note place="margin">Luk. 12.</note> 
               <hi>Euery one that confeſſeth me before men, the ſonne of man ſhall confeſſe him before the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels of God. And hee that denyeth mee before men, hee alſo ſhalbe denied before the Angels of GOD.</hi> This was the cauſe that made mee to take a prepo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterous waie, turning all things to mine own credit, when I ſhould haue turned them to the glorie of al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mightie God,<note place="margin">Matt. 6,</note> for our Sauiour ſaith: <hi>Firſt ſeeke the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:150763:5"/> of God and the righteouſnes of the ſame, and all other things ſhalbe giuen vnto you.</hi> Thus think<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to get credit by mine obſtinacie, I did looſe the fauour of God, the loue of my Soueraigne y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Quéenes moſt excellent Maieſtie, and the good will of all true ſubiects, which I hope to recouer againe, by this my frée Recantation, and my further conuerſation from henceforth in my Countrey.</p>
            <p>The third cauſe, was the tickling of vaine glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, and this cauſe I am ſure doth detaine moſt of the contrarie ſide in their peruerſe obſtinacie, howſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer they bragge that they ſéeke nothing by their dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings but the glorie of God. For, I was not mooued a little to ſubmitt my ſelfe to her Maieſties mercie, and to embrace the knowledge of the true fayth, ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the wicked counſell and deuilliſh deuiſes of the Pope and his Children, againſt the Quéenes moſt excellent Maieſtie, and our moſt déere Countrey. Which counſels I thought they woulde neuer haue put in execution. But when I ſaw that great prac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe come to paſſe, I meane y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> inuaſion of this Land, God ſo moouing me (as héereafter I will manifeſt) I thought vtterlie to forſake them, although couertlye for vaine gloryes ſake I continued a while amongſt them. I thought it then a goodly thing, and woorthy of commendation for mee, to defend an euill cauſe by probable reaſons. Yet I knew it was an hard thing for <hi>Anaxagoras</hi> to prooue that Snowe was blacke, or yncke white,<note place="margin">1. Cor. 1.</note> and for me to prooue light to be dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, or darknes to be light. For it is written, <hi>I wyll deſtroy the wiſedome of the wiſe, and caſt away the vnderſtanding of the prudent.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But now, ſéeing it hath pleaſed almighty God, to call me to the knowledge of his trueth,<note place="margin">2. Cor. 11</note> in deteſtation of this vaine glorie, I will ſaie with the Apoſtle: <hi>Si
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:150763:6"/> gloriari oportet, quae infirmitatis meae ſunt gloriabor,</hi> that is, <hi>If I muſt needes boaſt, I will boaſt in mine infyr<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitie.</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. Cor. 12</note> And againe, <hi>Libenter gloriabor in infirmitatibus meis, vt inhabitet in me virtus Chriſti:</hi> that is, <hi>I wyll gladlie boaſt in mine infirmities, that the power of Chriſt may dwell within me.</hi> Thus haue I bréefely declared the cauſes which draue me out of the waie, and cauſed me to delight in vanities, and follow lyes ſo long,<note place="margin">Pſal. 4.</note> that if Gods grace had not béene, I had béen cléene caſt awaie. But, now I ſaie againe, <hi>Impulſus euerſus ſum vt caderem et dominus ſuſcepit me,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 118</note> 
               <hi>I was ſore ſhaken that I was like to fall, but the Lorde hath vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holden mee.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But héere you will aſke mee the cauſe of ſo ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daine a change: I aunſwere, that I knowe no other but the grace of almightie GOD, the which wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth when and as it pleaſeth him. This grace haue I often refuſed for the cauſes before alledged: me thought I heard him ſaie vnto me dailie, <hi>Ecce ſto ad oſtium et pulſo,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Apo. 3.</note> 
               <hi>Behold I ſtand knocking at thy dores.</hi> Yet was I not aſhamed to thruſt him out, and to let in his aduerſarie the deuill. I hearde him cry within mée,<note place="margin">Cant. 5.</note> 
               <hi>Aperi mihi ſoror mea, amica mea, Columba mea, immaculata mea, caput meam plenum eſt rore, et cincinni mei guttis noctium: <hi>Ope<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vnto me my ſiſter, my friend, my Doue, my vnſpotted, my head is full of dew, and my locks with the droppes of the night.</hi>
               </hi> I heard him giue me theſe louing titles, but I refuſed him &amp; gaue him this aunſwer:<note place="margin">Ibidem.</note> 
               <hi>Expoliaui me tunica mea, quomodo induar illa? Laui pedes meos quomodo coinquinabo illos? <hi>I haue put off my coate, howe ſhall I put it on again? I haue waſhed my feete, howe ſhall I defile them a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine?</hi>
               </hi> Thus continued I, vntill hee by his grace ſo ſwéetly and forcibly preuented me, that whether I would or not, at length hee compelled my rebellious
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:150763:6"/> wyll to obey. So that I which once did ſo little ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of the true and auncient faith, that I counted it for an hereſie: now I ſée euidentlie, that without the ſame there is no waie to ſaluation.</p>
            <p>Therefore, if euer you pittied anie mans caſe, I beſéech you haue compaſſyon vpon mine, conſidering that it is a thing incident to ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s nature to erre and to ſin, but to continue and perſiſt in it, is the parte of the deuill. I freelie doo confeſſe &amp; acknowledge that I haue ſinned againſt God, my Prince,<note place="margin">Gen. 6.</note> and my Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey, as a man whoſe nature is prone, &amp; the thoughts of whoſe hart is alwaies bent to miſchiefe, I perſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted in mine errours a long time, as one that follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the ſuggeſtions of the Serpent, rather then the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpirations of the ſpirit of God. But by his motion, I am returned againe to the ſhéepfold of Chriſt. Wher<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fore I requeſt you all, for the tender mercies of God, that you would receiue mee that returne againe, fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing the ſteps of our Sauiour:<note place="margin">Luk. 15</note> who diſdained not to receiue Publicans and ſinners: who left <hi>99.</hi> ſhéepe in the wildernes and went to ſéeke one that was loſt. I haue béen like the prodigall Son, which looſely and wantonlie ſpent his portion in ryot &amp; luſte, and was compelled to eate ſuch meate as the Hogges did. All this haue I doone, I haue ſpent that Talent which God gaue me, in maintaining the harlot of <hi>Babylon,</hi> in vpholding the chaire of peſtilence, I meane the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> I haue fed my ſelfe with the ſwill and dregs of mens inuentions and traditions, forſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king the fountaine and foode of Gods worde. All this I haue doone: but at the laſt béeing by hunger com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pelled, I cryed out with that prodigall child, ſaying: <hi>Pater peccaui in caelum et coram te,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Luk. 15</note> 
               <hi>iam non ſum dignus vocari filius tuus: <hi>Father I haue ſinned againſt heauen and before thee, I am not woorthy to bee called anie
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:150763:7"/> more thy Son.</hi>
               </hi> This confeſſion mooued his Father to compaſſion, who louingly embraced him, receiued him willinglie, and cheriſhed him tenderlie. So I de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire you not to refuſe me, though I come late home, receiue me againe, and haue co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>paſſion. For our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour Chriſt ſaith,<note place="margin">Matt. 5.</note> 
               <hi>Beati miſericordes quoniam ipſi mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſericordiam conſequentur, <hi>Bleſſed are the mercifull for they ſhall obtaine mercie.</hi>
               </hi> And truely to haue com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſion is a thing wherein a man dooth followe the example of almightie GOD, for Chriſte himſelfe doth ſay,<note place="margin">Luke. 6</note> 
               <hi>Eſtote miſericordes ſicut pater veſter miſericors eſt, <hi>Be you mercifull as your Father is mercifull.</hi>
               </hi> Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue me I beſéech you which was a fugitiue, as one that repenteth, as one that deſireth rather to bee an abiect in Gods houſe,<note place="margin">Pſal. 84.</note> then to dwell in the Taberna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles of ſinners. His name therefore who hath ſo mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifully called me, be bleſſed for euermore.</p>
            <p>But nowe I will come to the purpoſe, that is, to recant and renounce ſuch errours, as heeretofore I haue maintained, deſiring God, that as it hath plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed his heauenly goodnes to giue me the grace to for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſake them, ſo it would alſo pleaſe him, to giue me the gift of perſeuerance to continue, that I may no more fall into them againe.</p>
            <p>You knowe it is the nature of the Serpent, to kéepe his head whole though he put his body in dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger for the defence of the ſame: but, if a man once bruſe his head, he can no longer endure againſt him but he muſt of neceſſitie die. And I can no better co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare the huge and weldie maſſe of Papiſtrie to anie thing, then vnto a Serpent, therefore in renouncing of it I will begin with the head.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The firſt Article of the Pope.</note>The Papiſts doo think, and I did thinke the ſame, that the Pope was Chriſt his Vicar, and ſupreame head of the vniuerſall Church héere vppon the earth
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:150763:7"/> militant. This Article béeing mightily vpholden, and ſtoutly defended, they thinke none other of their Bulwarks can be ſhaken. They thinke alſo that hee hath ſuch a prerogatiue, that he cannot erre, whereof ryſeth this preſumption in depoſing of Princes, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gradation of Biſhops, excomunication of all ſortes of people without reſpect, and of moſt light occaſion.</p>
            <p>Héereof hee preſumeth to preſcribe Lawes to the whole Church, the which forſooth without his dyſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſation muſt be inuiolable, <hi>Sub pena excommunica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionis.</hi> And whoſoeuer dooth breake them, if it be Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peror, King, Quéene, or what Prince ſoeuer, he muſt be depoſed, ſuch wickednes hath he practized againſt the Quéenes moſt excellent Maieſtie, to his vtter ſhame and confuſion, that the Prouerbe may bee ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>filled, God ſendeth a ſhrewde Cowe ſhorte hornes. But his holines, if it pleaſe you, is not co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tented with this: hee chalengeth to himſelfe ſo great a preroga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue, that hee wyll make and deface Articles of the Fayth at his owne will and pleaſure.<note place="margin">Gratian.</note> 
               <hi>Quia Dominus Deus noſter Papa.</hi> Héereof it ariſeth, that in that Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nagogue, ſcarce any of the Laye people can tel what they beléeue: for béeing aſked a reaſon of their faith, they ſaie nothing els, but thus beléeueth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Churche, thus ſaith the Pope. Whereas in deede, the reaſon of our Faith ſhould be taken from the word of God, for as the Pſalmiſt ſaith: <hi>Omnis homo mendax,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 116</note> 
               <hi>Euery man is a lyer.</hi> And therefore it ſhal ſuffiſe me that the Pope is a man, and conſequently a lyer, and may not onelie erre, but alſo hath already erred, which if I de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſired not to be briefe I woulde prooue, vnles by thys his ſupreame vſurped authority he be deified or made a God, which thing to confeſſe is not onely impuden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie but alſo intollerable blaſphemie. I therefore doe héere vtterly deteſt, abiure, and renounce him, with
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:150763:8"/> all his excommunications, interdictions, ſuſpenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, degradations, depoſitions, irregularities, and a thouſand ſuch like trifling thunderbolts. I pronounce alſo his doctrine, not to be according to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> holy Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, but contrarie vnto it, and therefore I doo freely and ioyfullie recant it, thanking GOD that it hath pleaſed his diuine Maieſtie to deliuer mee from the ſlauery of that Tyrant, deſiring him alſo that I may not fall into his ſubiection againe.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">2 Of the Maſſe.</note>Next vnto this is their blaſphemous doctrine of theyr Propitiatorie ſacrifice, which they cal the ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice of the Maſſe. This Maſſe I once did deuoutlie thinke vpon, hearde with great attention, and with great reuerence I did celebrate, onelie becauſe I thought it was indeede a ſacrifice, propitiatorie both for the liuing and the deade: when as the Scripture plainlie teſtifieth,<note place="margin">1. Pet. 4.</note> that <hi>Chriſtus ſemel pro peccatis no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtris mortuus eſt, iuſtus pro iniuſtis, vt nos offerret Deo, mortificatos quidem carne, viuificatos autem ſpiritu. <hi>Chriſt once died for our ſinnes, the iuſt for them that were vniuſt, that he might offer vs vp to God, morti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied in fleſhe, but quickned in ſpirite.</hi>
               </hi> Hetherto alſo dooth all the Epiſtle to the <hi>Hebrewes</hi> tende. It was alſo commaunded the High Prieſt in the olde Law, that hee ſhoulde enter into <hi>Sancta Sanctorum</hi> but once in the yéere, which ſimilitude the Apoſtle, in the ſame Epiſtle, applyeth vnto y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> onely ſacrifice which Chriſt offered for our ſins vpon the Croſſe. The which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he hath once doone, I think it vnlawful to haue any more propitiatorie Sacrifices then that one of our Sauiour Chriſt. And therefore that which they call the propitiatory Sacrifice of the Maſſe, I thinke it rather to be a derogatorie blaſphemie to the paſſy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Ieſus Chriſt. And for that cauſe I denie that either it is a Sacrifice, or auailable for the lyuing,
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:150763:8"/> much leſſe for the dead. I doo alſo from henceforth vt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly denounce it to be wicked, and an Idoll.</p>
            <p>Tranſubſtantiation,<note place="margin">3 Of tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſubſtanti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation, and reall pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence.</note> a terme inuented in the <hi>La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terane Counſell,</hi> vnder Pope <hi>Innocentius</hi> the thyrde of that name, to eſtabliſh an other error as groſſe as it ſelfe, that is to ſay: The Reall preſence of Chriſte his bodie in the Sacrament (as they call it) of the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tar: is contrarie not onelie to Fayth, but alſo to natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall reaſon. For the holy Scripture teacheth vs, that <hi>Chriſt is aſcended into heauen,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mar. 16.</note> 
               <hi>&amp; ſitteth at the right hand of God.</hi> And alſo that it was thought conueni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent that heauen ſhould containe him, not according to his diuinitie, which is incomprehenſible,<note place="margin">Act. 3.</note> but accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to his humane nature which is circumſcripti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, or to bee contained in one place, for he tooke not onelie the bodie of man vpon him, but alſo the paſſy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of a naturall bodie, and therefore hath his proper place. But if they will néedes haue him preſent in manie places at once, they muſt alſo denie y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he hath a bodie, and conſent to the <hi>Eutichian</hi> hereſey, and ſaie there was a commiſtion of the diuine and humaine nature, which <hi>Athanaſius</hi> in his Creede denieth,<note place="margin">Athanaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us in Sym<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bolo.</note> ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing: <hi>Neque commiſtionem paſſus, neque diuiſionem, <hi>ney<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſuffering mixture nor diuiſion.</hi>
               </hi> Yet of this mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter was I neuer ſo fully perſwaded, but that ſtill I had ſome doubt of it. And now I renounce it, crauing pardon of God, for defending that which I alwayes doubted of.</p>
            <p>The number of the Sacraments in the Church,<note place="margin">4 Number of Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments.</note> I acknowledge is no more then two, that is to witt, Baptiſme, and the Lords Supper, and theſe two I finde to be inſtituted by Chriſt himſelfe in the holye Goſpell. The other fiue which they adde, which are, Confirmation, Penaunce, Extreame vnction, Order, and Matrimonie: Becauſe I know not where to find
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:150763:9"/> them, neither by the inſtitution of Chriſt, nor in the Goſpell or Newe Teſtament, I count them not for Sacraments: for I thinke none to haue authority to make Sacraments but God onely, and therfore thoſe two I thinke to be Sacraments and none other.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">5 Prayer to Saints.</note>They make a great ſtriuing and ſtrugling to main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine Prayer, and inuocation to the Saints depar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, thinking the mediation of our Lorde and Aduo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate Ieſus Chriſt inſufficient for vs: This inuoca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, I did thinke béeing in that Sinagogue, to bee a neceſſarie and a conuenient thing, although for the ſame I coulde finde no ground in the word of GOD. Yet one thing in the ſame, béeing as I thought then an abuſe, I knewe not howe to excuſe: and that was the inuocation of diuers Saints for diuers purpoſes. As, one againſt the plague, as S. <hi>Sebaſtian.</hi> An other againſt the tootheake, as S. <hi>Appolonia.</hi> Another a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the falling ſicknes, as S. <hi>Chriſtopher,</hi> and dyuers other. As though almightie God coulde not heare vs but by the helpe of theſe Saints. And thus in calling vpon them, we derogate from the glorie of almightie God. But they ſay, they deſire them but to pray for them, and aſke no other grace at theyr handes. Then woulde I gladly knowe of them why they vſe theſe verſes in theyr office of S. <hi>Peter ad vincula.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <l>Solue iubente deo terrarum Petre cathenas,</l>
               <l>Qui facis vt pateant caeleſtia regna beatis.</l>
            </q>
            <p>In Engliſh thus,
<q>
                  <l>O Peter looſe as God commaunds, from vs the earthly chayne,</l>
                  <l>The which to bleſſed me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> doſt make, the gate of heauen plaine.</l>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>☞ And in a Hymne of the ſame.</p>
            <q>
               <l>Iam bone paſtor Petre clemens accipe,</l>
               <l>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ota precantum et peccati vincula,</l>
               <l>Reſolue tibi poteſtate tradita,</l>
               <l>Qua cunctis caelum verbo claudis aperis.</l>
            </q>
            <pb n="17" facs="tcp:150763:9"/>
            <p>In Engliſh thus.</p>
            <q>
               <l>Nowe ſheepeheard good, ô Peter milde receiue,</l>
               <l>The vowes with prayer which we yeeld to thee:</l>
               <l>By that ſame power which God to thee did giue,</l>
               <l>Which mak'ſt the skyes be ſhut, and wide to bee.</l>
            </q>
            <p>One thing I meruaile at, that as yet the aduer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaries béeing in controuerſie, whether the Saints do ſée God or not, and yet graunting that Saints can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not heare the praiers of the liuing but by the ſight of God, why ſo obſtinatly they defende this point? And nowe, whereas before I counted it neceſſarie &amp; con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenient, I count it vaine, and ſuperfluous, and take it for an errour.</p>
            <p>Againe, prayer for the deade,<note place="margin">6 Prayer for the dead</note> is a point of great Religion amongſt them: which Article they ground vpon an other, no leſſe abſurde then it ſelfe, and that is Purgatorie, which Purgatorie I ſée not howe they can defende by Scripture, though they ſéeme contentiouſly to wreſt certaine places of the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, from the true meaning of the ſame vnto theyr owne meaning, and all to defende this groſſe errour of theirs. For they ſay that thoſe ſoules that depart out of this life with anie veniall ſinne, or els with the Reliques of mortall ſinne: muſt néedes bee pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged after this life before they can come to Heauen.</p>
            <p>This is a groſſe error and is taken out of the Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>et <hi>Virgil,</hi> for in that place where hee bringeth <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiſes,</hi> to enſtruct his Sonne <hi>Aeneas</hi> of theyr ſtate in hell, he ſpeaketh on this ſort.</p>
            <q>
               <l>Quin et ſupremo cum lumine vita reliquit</l>
               <l>Non tamen omne malum miſeris,<note place="margin">Aeneid. 6.</note> nec funditus omnes</l>
               <l>Corporea excedunt peſtes, penituſque neceſſe eſt,</l>
               <l>Multa diu concreta modis violeſcere miris.</l>
               <l>Ergo excutentur paenis, veterumque malorum</l>
               <l>Supplina expendunt, aliae pautuntur inanes,</l>
               <pb n="18" facs="tcp:150763:10"/>
               <l>Suſpenſae ad uentos, aliis ſab gurgite vaſto</l>
               <l>Infectum eluitur ſcelks, aut exuritur igni,</l>
               <l>Quiſque ſuos patimur manes, exinde per amplum</l>
               <l>Mittimur Elyſium et pauci laeta arua tenemus.</l>
            </q>
            <p>In Engliſh thus.</p>
            <q>
               <l>And alſo when the pleſant life is gone with gladſome light,</l>
               <l>Yet euery, miſchiefe from thoſe ſoules is not departed quite,</l>
               <l>Nor plague of body yet is gone, and ſo it needfull is,</l>
               <l>That many things ſhould them deſteine which once haue been amis.</l>
               <l>Therfore they ſuffer puniſhment, &amp; for offences paſt,</l>
               <l>They haue their meed, of bluſtring winds, ſome feele the bitter blaſt</l>
               <l>And ſome in botto<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of a gulfe do waſh their faults away,</l>
               <l>And ſome with flames of ſcorching fire, for paſſed ſins do pay,</l>
               <l>Each one of vs his paine doth feele, and then exempt fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> paine,</l>
               <l>We walk about theſe pleaſant fields a very little trayne.</l>
            </q>
            <p>This Article therfore with the reſt, is ſuperſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious, vaine and ridiculous.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">7. Workes of Supere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogation,</note>Workes of ſupererogation as they call them, are ſo vaine and fooliſh, that I meruaile that wyſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men at anie time will confeſſe any ſuch to bee. For the holie Scripture ſayth, that when we haue doone all that we can, we muſt call our ſelues vnprofitable ſeruaunts. Truelie for my part, I knowe not why they ſhould ſo bind God vnto our works, that if wée doo them, he cannot chooſe but ſaue vs. For all that we can doo commeth from God, and we are bound to followe, and accept of the good inſpirations of him. But this worde Supererogation, dooth ſignifie that the worke which we doo, is more then we are bound to doo, which taketh awaie the grace of God as the <hi>Pelagean</hi> dooth, and fortifieth our fréewill ſo much, as though it had neuer béen loſt. But truely I think and beléeue our Fréewill to be ſo wounded, that not onely it is not able to doo more the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> we ought, but al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo it can not performe y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> which we ought to doo. Let them of the aduerſary part contend and wrangle ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer ſo much to the contrarie. The grounde of thys
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:150763:10"/> their vngrounded doctrine,<note place="margin">Luk. 10.</note> is taken out of the Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble of the <hi>Samaritane,</hi> which tooke compaſſion vpon him, who diſcending from <hi>Ieruſalem</hi> to <hi>Iericho,</hi> was wounded by Théeues. For paying the Hoſte of the houſe for his charges, he told him that whatſoeuer he laid out more the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he had giuen him, at his return he would pay him againe. Yet conſider they not, that in that Parable our Sauiour exhorteth vs to mutu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all loue &amp; neighbourly charitie, and that euery man is bounde to doo good vnto his neighbour in time of néede.</p>
            <p>They denie that faith is ſufficient to iuſtifie vs in Gods ſight, without our owne merits,<note place="margin">8 Good woorkes.</note> contrary to the doctrine of the Apoſtle in his Epiſtles to the <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maines,</hi> and <hi>Galathians.</hi> For good works are indeede required at our handes, not as the cauſe, but as the effect of our iuſtification. And for this cauſe workes are required at our hands, to be a teſtimonie of our Faith, and a cauſe that other men may giue the glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie vnto God: for our Sauiour ſaith,<note place="margin">Math. 5.</note> 
               <hi>Sic luceat lux veſtra coram hominibus, vt videant opera veſtra bona et glorificent Patrem veſtrum qui eſt in caelis. <hi>So let your light ſhyne before men, that they may ſee your good works, and glorifie your Father which is in heauen.</hi>
               </hi> Then is it conſequent, that our iuſtificatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> commeth no waies of our ſelues, but onely by faith in Chriſt Ieſus.</p>
            <p>After this followeth a moſt ridiculous doctrine,<note place="margin">9 Indul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gences and pardons.</note> of the Popes Indulgences and pardons, wherein he dooth moſt inſolently arrogate to himſelf, the diſpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſations of Chriſt his paſſion, applying that to the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giuenes of ſins, the forme of which hath an arrogant kind of ſpéech, as thus. If a man faſt one Friday with bread and water, he ſhal haue <hi>plenarie indulgence,</hi> and if he faſt ſo on another day, his pardon ſhalbe limit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:150763:11"/> for certaine yéeres, as <hi>10000.</hi> &amp;c. or ſome ſuch like, or els <hi>a pena et culpa.</hi> I alwaies thought theſe trifles vaine, but now I ſée the blaſphemie of them. For it is ſcant poſſible to get theſe great Indulgen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, but by wearing a paire of Beades, or a Graine, Medall, Crucifixe, Picture, <hi>Agnus Dei,</hi> or ſuch like tromperie. It would be too tedious to ſet downe the manifold kinds of theſe. Indulgences, which al tend to one ende, that is, to the leſſening of the vertue of Chriſt his paſſion.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">10 Images. <hi>Exo. 20.</hi>
               </note>The ſeconde commaundement plainly forbiddeth vs to make or to haue any grauen Image, or y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of any thing to worſhip it. But the aduerſarie excommunicateth them that denie the neceſſitie of Images in Churches, as it is to be ſéene in dyuers of their Counſels. For ſay they, it is lawfull, not onlie to retaine them, but alſo to worſhip the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. The which if it be not againſt the ſeconde commaundement, let them looke vnto it, I for mine owne part doo ſée it, and am aſhamed that euer I was ſo blockiſh, as to thinke a block or a ſtone to bee neceſſarie or godlie, I thought it ſo once, but nowe I cannot be ſo perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded. For he that hath any reaſon in him to diſcourſe, or ſence to perceiue, cannot be ſo void of reaſon, or ſo ſenceleſſe as to exhibit honor or reuerence to a ſenc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe Image, when the ſame Image, if it had ſence, would not onely refuſe that worſhip, but alſo would willingly fall downe to worſhip or adore the work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man that made it.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">11 Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion in both kinds</note>They hold and defend that the Laye people may not receiue y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Communion vnder both kinds, which doctrine is repugnant to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> inſtitution of Chriſt. For he ſaid vnto the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that were preſent with him at hys laſt Supper, <hi>Take and eate, and drinke ye all of this.</hi> For though the aduerſary ſay, that the Laye people
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:150763:11"/> haue not the priuiledge to receiue the Cup, becauſe the Apoſtles who onely were preſent at that ſupper were Prieſtes, and not Laye men: it holdeth not, for by the ſame reaſon, a man may alſo barre the Laye people from receiuing of either kinde, for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Apoſtles were Prieſts, and only preſent at the Supper, <hi>ergo</hi> it is vnlawful for any to be pertaker of that Supper but onlie Prieſts. And yet Chriſt himſelfe in ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther place ſaith,<note place="margin">Ioh. 6.</note> 
               <hi>Vnles you eate my fleſh and drinke my blood, you ſhall haue no life in you.</hi> And theſe words he ſpake not only to the Apoſtles, but <hi>Turbis Iudeorum,</hi> to the company of the Iewes, and therfore I count their dealings iniurious to the people, their doctrine blaſphemous, &amp; their proofe to no purpoſe.</p>
            <p>Finallie, all ſuch Articles,<note place="margin">12 Dyuers other Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticles.</note> which are repugnaunt to the word of God: I vtterly refuſe, as in ſpeciall, the Seruice in an vnknowne tongue, the prohibiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the reading of Scriptures to the Laye people, the forbidding of the tranſlation of the ſame into a vulgare tongue, Pylgrimages, Vowes, and to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude, all ſuch Articles, as are contrarie to the Arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles of Religion, ſet downe by publique authoritie, I doo vtterly renounce and abiure: and on the other ſide, I doo willingly, and without compulſion, and gladly with reuerence, receiue, embrace, and fréelie profeſſe, the ſayde Articles ſet forth by publique au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority, as doctrine without ſuperſtition, and moſt agréeable to the word of God.</p>
            <p>Thus haue I generally recanted mine errours in matters of Religion, and nowe, will I accuſe my ſelfe and my dealings, touching my diſobedience to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards my Soueraigne the Quéenes moſt excellent Maieſtie. I haue moſt ſtubbornly and wilfullye tranſgreſſed her Maieſties Lawes. Knowing firſt the offence of going beyond the Seas, and yet caring
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:150763:12"/> not for that, I procéeded further, and willinglie was prieſted at <hi>Rome.</hi> Thirdly, maliciouſly I came into my Countrey, with a will to ſeduce her Ma. Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iects from the true and ſincere Religion, and make the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſubiects to that tyranny, vnto the which I was my ſelfe ſubiect. Then being baniſhed, I returned a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine into my Countrey, with the ſame intent that I came in firſt, and for theſe great faultes of myne I am moſt hartily ſorrie, and in the bowels of Gods infinite mercy, I deſire all them, that any waies by my meanes haue béene deceiued, &amp; doo nowe repent, to forgiue me. Likewiſe thoſe that haue not as yet their harts mooued by my example, to forſake theyr errours, and amend their opinions.</p>
            <p>Thus firſt of all I aſke forgiuenes of almightie God, whom like a moſt ingratefull &amp; wilful wretch, I haue moſt gréeuouſly offended. Firſt, in abuſing his gifts, which of his fatherly goodnes he had be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtowed vpon me. Secondly, in refuſing and reiecting his holy inſpirations. And laſtly, by prouoking o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers to offend by my example. And all this haue I doone, not like vnto them, vnto whom our Sauiour promiſeth a milder iudgment in the latter day: but like vnto them of whom S. <hi>Paule</hi> ſpeaketh: Which when they knew God,<note place="margin">Rom. 1.</note> did not honor him as GOD was to be honoured, and therfore my damnation had béene the greater if I had perſiſted. But ſéeing that it hath pleaſed him, which hath preſerued mee from my Mothers, wombe to call mee to his wonderfull light, I deſire you all that are héere preſent, to giue him thankes for the ſame: for there is more ioy in heauen before the Angels of God, for the conuerſion of one ſinner,<note place="margin">Luk. 15.</note> then for <hi>99.</hi> iuſt perſons which neede no repentaunce. Deſiring alſo his diuine Maieſtie, that he would not remember mine olde wickednes
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:150763:12"/> and follie:<note place="margin">Pſal. 143</note> for if he would enter into iudgment with his Seruants, there ſhoulde none be iuſtified in hys ſight. But that he would think on the paſſion of our Sauiour Ieſus Chriſt, by the which hee hath moſt mercifully redéemed mee, deſiring him alſo, that it hath pleaſed his diuine Maieſtie, to call mee to the light of his trueth: ſo it woulde pleaſe him to bring al them which now do liue in blindnes, to the ſame. Secondly, with humble hart I aſke forgiuenes of the Quéenes Maieſtie, moſt humbly ſubmitting my ſelfe to the mercy of ſo godly a Prince, whom when ſhe called her Subiects to their duetie &amp; obedience, not by ſeueritie and rigor of the Law, but like a pit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifull mother, by mercie: I haue not onely not heard her, but alſo, (with ſorrow I ſpeake it) I haue con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temned and ſet light by.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, I aſke forgiuenes of you that bee héere preſent, in whom I thinke that I ſée all my Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trymen preſent: deſiring you to forgiue all ſuch of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fences, as I haue committed againſt GOD, the Quéenes Maieſtie, and againſt you.</p>
            <closer>God ſaue the Queene.</closer>
            <closer>
               <signed>Me ita ſentire ſicut ſcripſi teſtor Deum. Guilielmus Tedderus.</signed>
            </closer>
            <pb facs="tcp:150763:13"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:150763:13"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:150763:14"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:150763:14" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:150763:15"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
